<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Combine on Huong Do</title><link>/tags/combine/</link><description>Recent content in Combine on Huong Do</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Huong Do</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 10:00:02 +0701</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/combine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Async Sequence instead of Combine?</title><link>/posts/async-sequence-combine/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 10:00:02 +0701</pubDate><guid>/posts/async-sequence-combine/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since WWDC 2021, I’ve seen folks getting excited about the introduction of Swift concurrency, a.k.a async/await. It’s very common to come across comments that async/await will soon replace Combine, due to its potential and friendliness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR&lt;/strong&gt;: The motivation of this post is to discover the power of &lt;a href="https://href.li/?https://developer.apple.com/documentation/Swift/AsyncSequence"&gt;AsyncSequence&lt;/a&gt; when used with &lt;a href="https://href.li/?https://github.com/apple/swift-async-algorithms"&gt;Async Algorithms&lt;/a&gt;, to see if we can use it in place of Combine. To be more specific, I’m curious to see if we can use it with SwiftUI to handle form validation – one of my favorite applications of Combine when working with SwiftUI.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Combine from RxSwift - Highlights for smooth adaption</title><link>/posts/combine-from-rxswift/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 21:23:02 +0700</pubDate><guid>/posts/combine-from-rxswift/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;RxSwift has been around since 2015 and widely known among Apple developer community as an efficient open-sourced FRP library. In WWDC 2019 Apple introduced their very own FRP framework, making it possible to utilize the paradigm natively with declarative Swift API. The two frameworks share quite a few similarities in terms of principles and usage, so it can be not too daunting to get your feet wet with Combine if you have already been using RxSwift in your projects.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>